{"tossups": [{"question": "The speaker of this oration defended his wife by noting that she was born on St. Patrick\u2019s Day, and the Irish never quit. A \u201ctwo-year-old Oldsmobile\u201d and loans from Riggs Bank were recounted in this speech, which was a response to concerns that a fund used to reimburse its speaker for travel expenses was a source of corruption. Its speaker noted that Pat did not have a mink coat, but that his children loved the central figure and would be keeping it. For the point, name this 1952 televised speech by Richard Nixon, named for the cocker spaniel he intended to keep.", "answer": "<b> Checkers</b> speech (accept descriptions of the Nixon<b> Fund</b> speech before \u201cfund\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This writer described \u201cthe cold stars lighting, very old and bleak / in different skies\u201d in the poem \u201cI Saw His Round Mouth\u2019s Crimson.\u201d In one of his poems, the narrator is told \u201chere is no cause to mourn\u201dby a former enemy he meets in Hell. This author of \u201cStrange Meeting\u201d described an \u201cecstasy of fumbling\u201din response to nerve gas in a poem that calls a patriotic Horace quote \u201cthe old Lie\u201d. For the point, name this British World War I poet of \u201cDulce et Decorum Est.\u201d", "answer": "Wilfred<b> Owen</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "One ruler with this name introduced the Siete Partidas Law Code. The Fifth Siege of Gibraltar ended when a ruler of this name died from the bubonic plague. Maria Christina of Austria served as regent for a ruler of this name, and signed the Treaty of Paris on his behalf to end war with the United States. One ruler with this named backed the dictatorship of Miguel Primo de Rivera, which led to his overthrow. For the point, give this name of thirteen Kings of Castile and Spain.", "answer": "<b> Alfonso</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The inspiration for this political party was the disappearance of William Morgan, and it was supported by the<em> Enquirer</em>, published by Thurlow Weed. This party held the first presidential nominating convention; it chose William Wirt, who won Vermont\u2019s electoral votes in 1832. This party was gradually absorbed by another anti-Democratic party, the Whigs, because it enjoyed a broader platform. For the point, name this 19th century political party whose primary goal was the downfall of a certain secret society.", "answer": "<b> Anti-Masonic</b> Party", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The<em> Scharnhorst</em> and<em> Gneisenau</em> were sunk in one battle fought at this location. Operation Mikado was a major offensive launched over this location, where Exocet missiles sunk the<em> Sheffield</em>. Admiral Graf von Spee was killed in 1914 at this location, where the<em> General Belgrano</em> was later sunk in a war sparked by Leopoldo Galtieri that boosted the popularity of Margaret Thatcher. For the point, name these islands contested by Great Britain and Argentina in a 1980s war.", "answer": "<b> Falkland</b> Islands (or Islas<b> Malvinas</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In 2001, Trent Dilfer was chosen to deliver this phrase instead of Ray Lewis, possibly due to Lewis\u2019connection to a double murder. The first commercial use of this phrase was by Phil Simms in January 1987. This phrase is often recorded twice, with different names, for marketing purposes, and is traditionally accompanied by the song \u201cWhen You Wish Upon a Star\u201d. For the point, give this phrase traditionally spoken by the newly-announced Super Bowl MVP as a response to the question \u201cWhat are you going to do next?\u201d", "answer": "<b> \u201dI\u2019m going to</b> (Walt)<b> Disney World!\u201d</b> or<b> \u201dI\u2019m going to</b> (Walt)<b> Disney Land!\u201d</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This was the first woman to be crowned with St. Edward\u2019s Crown, which was usually reserved for males. The \u201cSpanish Chronicle\u201d describes how Thomas Cromwell plotted to remove this figure from power. She was allegedly betrothed to Henry Percy before that arrangement was broken by Cardinal Wolsey. This figure\u2019s downfall came when Mark Smeaton confessed to being her lover, and she was replaced by Jane Seymour. For the point, name this second wife of Henry VIII and mother of Elizabeth I.", "answer": "Anne<b> Boleyn</b> (prompt on Anne)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This party lost an election thanks to James Soong\u2019s third party run. Politicians not in this party were forced to run as Tangwai candidates. In its country\u2019s most recent presidential election, it was defeated by the DPP candidate Tsai Ingwen, who will replace its current head, Ma Ingjeu. This party\u2019s monopoly on cigarettes caused an incident that was followed by the White Terror, the 228 Uprising. For the point, name this party founded by Sun Yat-Sen, which fled to Taiwan after losing the Chinese Civil War.", "answer": "<b> Kuomintang</b> (or<b> KMT</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "One of this man\u2019s paintings depicts a meeting in Shackamaxon. His painting of the Treaty of Paris remained unfinished when the British delegation refused to pose. Another of his canvases, which broke with the established tradition of using classical dress for historical painting, depicted a victorious British general dying from his musket wounds on the Plains of Abraham. For the point, name this Anglo-American painter of<em> Penn\u2019s Treaty With The Indians</em> and<em> The Death of General Wolfe</em>.", "answer": "Benjamin<b> West</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<em>Ableman v. Booth</em> ruled Wisconsin\u2019s overturning of this law unconsitutional. Richard Henry Dana protested how this law, which was prompted by the ruling in<em> Prigg v Pennsylvania</em>, was applied to Anthony Burns in Boston. This law, alternatively known as the \u201cBloodhound Law,\u201d was supported within a broader compromise by Daniel Webster\u2019s \u201cSeventh of March\u201d speech. For the point, name this law, passed as part of the Compromise of 1850, which required captured slaves to be returned to their masters.", "answer": "<b> Fugitive Slave</b> Act (or Law or Bill)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In one work, this thinker described private property as an \u201cabstract right,\u201d rather than a natural one. A critique of one of this thinker\u2019s works introduced the quote \u201creligion is the opium of the people.\u201d A\u201cStruggle to the death\u201d takes place between self-conscious beings in this thinker\u2019s master-slave dialectic. Karl Popper\u2019s<em> The Open Society and its Enemies</em> argued that Plato, Karl Marx, and this thinker were the intellectual origins of 20th century totalitarianism. For the point, name this German philosopher who wrote<em> The Phenomenology of Spirit</em>.", "answer": "Georg Wilhelm Friedrich<b> Hegel</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This landmass is the site of the southern terminus of an 800-mile-long, narrow-gauge railway whose construction was halted by World War I. One general from this region won the Battles of Hira and River to its north and the Battle of Chains within it. The Hejaz Railway runs through this peninsula, where the Rashiduns flourished. For the point, name this Middle Eastern peninsula whose land is dominated by a country led by the House of Saud.", "answer": "<b> Arabia</b>n Peninsula (accept<b> Hejaz</b> (Railway) before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This man was promoted to Major General after a victory at the Battle of Ridgefield. He led a force that raided New London as part of the Battle of Groton Heights. During one battle, this man was injured while attempting to take the Breymann Redoubt; that injury is memorialized by a statue of a boot. As a result of that battle, this man was stripped of his position by Horatio Gates, after which this man contacted Henry Clinton. For the point, name this American general who conspired to handover West Point to the British.", "answer": "Benedict<b> Arnold</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This dynasty established various Protectorates General to pacify the East, West and North. Huang Chao led a military uprising against this dynasty shortly after he massacred tens of thousands of Arabs and Jews in Guangzhou. This dynasty was briefly usurped by the Zhou Dynasty under Empress Wu Zetian, and was briefly replaced by the State of Yan after an uprising led by a half Sogdian half Turkish general. For the point, name this Chinese dynasty that faced the An Lushan rebellion and succeeded the Sui Dynasty.", "answer": "<b> Tang</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Robert Toombs opposed this conflict, saying \u201cWe had territory enough, Heaven knew.\u201d When the House of Representatives voted to honor officers who served in this conflict, John Quincy Adams loudly voted no, then suffered a cerebral hemorrhage and died two days later. As a representative, Abraham Lincoln doubted the validity of this war via the Spot Resolutions, and a philosopher refused to support either slavery or this war by paying his poll tax, as noted in<em> Civil Disobedience</em>. For the point, name this 1840s war, unpopular in the North due to fears that slavery would expand in new territory won along the Rio Grande.", "answer": "<b> Mexican-American</b> War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A five-act opera by this man includes an auto-da-f\u00b4e scene and ends with former Emperor Charles V disguised as a monk, dragging his grandson into a tomb. This composer of<em> Don Carlos</em> wrote the \u201cChorus of Hebrew Slaves\u201d for his opera<em> Nabucco</em>, which became an anthem of the Risorgimento. In another of his operas the Duke of Mantua sings \u201cLa donna e mobile\u201d and was targeted for assassination by the title hunchbacked jester. For the point, name this Italian composer of<em> Rigoletto</em>.", "answer": "Giuseppe<b> Verdi</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "This event was precipitated by the directions of a farmer leading to a place known as \u201cOld Peak.\u201dThe party at the forefront of this event had sailed down the Urubamba River in their search for Vitcos. Pictures of the Altar of the Condors and Inti Watana stone were taken as a result of this event, which was believed by one participant to have taken place at Vilcabamba, where citizens had fled after the conquests of Pizarro\u2019s conquistadors. For the point, name this 1911 event in which a party led by Yale\u2019s Hiram Bingham \u201cdiscovered\u201d an eminent Incan city.", "answer": "<b> discovery of Machu Picchu</b> (\u201ddiscovery\u201d not needed after mentioned; accept descriptions, especially those that say that locals knew about it the whole time)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 2012, footage of this team surfaced, showing it divided up for \u201cthe Greatest Game Nobody Ever Saw\u201d during a scrimmage in Monaco. Rod Thorn was warned that one member of this team would quit if Isiah Thomas were selected, so Clyde Drexler and Christian Laettner were the final selected members. Chuck Daly never called a timeout as coach of this team, the first of its kind to employ professionals. For the point, name this team led by Magic Johnson, Larry Bird, and Michael Jordan, which resoundingly won the gold medal in Barcelona.", "answer": "the<b> Dream Team</b> (accept 19<b>92 U.S.</b> Olympic men\u2019s<b> basketball</b> team, prompting on partial answers)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The Blum-Violette proposal granted citizenship to some people from this country. A plaque on the Saint-Michel bridge commemorates a massacre of people from this country ordered by Maurice Papon; that was the Paris Massacre of 1961. Harkis are French Muslim soldiers from this country, and the Oran massacres targeted French pied-noirs in this country. For the point, name this country, a former French colony and the site of the Algiers Putsch.", "answer": "<b> Algeria</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This publication falsely predicted the death of Titan Leed, which led this publication to insist that the still-alive Leed was an impostor. It took its name from the author of<em> Rider\u2019s British Merlin</em>. This publication was said to be written by an astronomer in its early years, before that character was re-written as a dull, thrifty countryman.<em> The Way of Wealth</em> is a collection of sayings from this publication, including\u201cearly to bed and early to rise, makes a man healthy, wealthy, and wise.\u201d For the point, name this pseudonymously-published almanac by Benjamin Franklin.", "answer": "<b> Poor Richard\u2019s</b> Almanac", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "Phineas Miller sold this invention at exorbitant rates after it was first created in Catherine Greene\u2019s workshop. William Longstreet improved upon this invention with his \u201cbreast roller.\u201d Its inventor made his fortune in gunsmithing after his patent for this creation was ignored. This machine used a rotating cylinder to move small hooks and brushes. For the point, name this machine invented by Eli Whitney that separated lint from seed in a slavery-intensive textile crop.", "answer": "mechanical<b> cotton gin</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During his intervention in Bavaria, this ruler was victorious in the Battle of the Rain. This man was wounded trying to cross the Vistula during a war against Poland that ended with the Treaty of Altmark. This man allegedly claimed that \u201cthe Lord God is my armor\u201d before fighting without protection and dying at the Battle of Lutzen. Axel Oxenstierna ruled as a regent after the death of, for the point, what\u201cLion of the North,\u201d who fought in the Thirty Years War as King of Sweden?", "answer": "<b> Gustavus Adolphus</b> (or<b> Gustav Adolf</b>; accept additional mentions of \u201cthe Great\u201d or \u201cthe Second\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This conflict was called for in the bull<em> Post Miserabile</em>. Baldwin of Flanders was chosen over Boniface of Montferrat for the position of Latin Emperor during this conflict. The Siege of Zara during this conflict was led by a 90-year-old blind man. Alexius IV was made emperor during this conflict, which was called for by Pope Innocent III. Enrico Dandolo led forces in, for the point, which early 13th century Christian attempt to conquer Jerusalem that, instead, occupied the Byzantine Empire and founded the Latin Empire?", "answer": "<b> Fourth Crusade</b> (prompt on Crusade(s)) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Mikael Agricola translated the New Testament into the language of this country. Kurt Wallenius was imprisoned after leading an uprising in Mantsala by the Lapua Movement in this country, whose White Guard defeated the Red Guard during a civil war. The Grand Duchy of this modern day country was established shortly after the Diet of Porvoo. Frederick Charles of Hesse was briefly king of, for the point, what Scandinavian country whose capital is Helsinki?", "answer": "<b> Finland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}